Guide to the Career Center Office records, 1938-2000
Duke University. University Archives
Career Center Office records 1938-2000
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Career Center.
1.2 linear feet Extent: 1,200 Items
Contains the records of the Appointments Office, a career placement service for students of Duke University. The Appointments Office was later known as the Office of Placement Services and Career Development Center and is currently (2007) known as the Career Center. This collection also contains professional correspondence, writings, and speeches of Fannie Y. Mitchell, director of the Appointments Office from 1947-1968. Types of materials include correspondence, speeches, short writings, conference presentation materials, annual reports, minutes, newsletters, fliers, clippings, and a photograph. Major subjects include Duke University students, the Appointments Office, Office of Placement Services history, Fannie Y. Mitchell, student employment, recruiting, and career guidance. Materials range in date from 1938-2000.
uacareer
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Career Center Office records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1968, 1993.
Biographical and Historical Note
The Duke University Appointments Office, a student career placement service, was created around 1938. James Simpson was the first director, serving from 1938 until 1940. When he left in 1940, William Upchurch assumed the position of Director, and he remained in charge until 1942. Fannie Mitchell came to the Appointments Office in 1942 and was acting director until she assumed the full responsibilities of director in 1947. She was the first woman to hold the position of director.
The Appointments Office originally placed students in either teaching or commercial positions, but by the 1950s had expanded the scope of their placement efforts to include a variety of fields. The Appointments Office has helped students locate career leads by inviting representatives of companies to come to campus to interview students. The Appointments Office also counseled students on job searching, interviewing skills, resume writing, and compiled confidential evaluation records of student recommendations.
Fannie Mitchell was a well-connected professional in college recruiting. She relied on acquaintances in the United States and abroad to secure choice recruiters to come to campus, and to further the positive image of Duke University graduates. Mitchell participated in many Duke University conferences regarding the employability of Duke University graduates, and women's achievement in the workplace, and she also advised many academic departments on the interests of recruiters. Mitchell also served on the Woman's College Advisory Committee.
Mitchell held leadership positions in professional organizations including the Southern College Placement Association, College Placement Services, Southern Education Foundation, Western College Placement Association, Durham Business and Professional Women's Club Federation, and the State Business and Professional Women's Club Federation.
When Fannie Mitchell retired from her position in 1968, an endowment created in her honor established the Fannie Mitchell Conference on Career Choices. There is also a Fannie Mitchell student scholarship. Patricia O’Conner succeeded Fanny Mitchell becoming the director in 1968. In 1969, the office was renamed Office of Placement Services. Laurence Maskel was the director from 1988 to 1990, and in 1990 the named of the department changed to the Career Development Center. John Noble became director of the Center in 1991. The department is currently (2007) known as the Career Center.
The Career Center continues to serve all Duke University students and works with academic departments to develop industry-specific job searching strategies. As of 2003, the Career Center of Duke University is a department of the Division of Student Affairs.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the Appointments Office (now known as Duke Career Center) and professional papers of Fannie Y. Mitchell, director of the Appointments Office. Materials range in date from 1938-2000.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
College placement services.; College Placement Services (U.S.); Counseling in higher education -- United States.; Duke University. Appointments Office -- History.; Duke University. Office of Placement Services -- History.; Duke University. Career Center -- History.; Employees -- Recruiting -- United States.; Mitchell, Fannie Yarbrough.; Southern College Placement Association -- History.; Vocational guidance -- United States.
Related Material
Appointments Office, Annual Reports, 1945-1972
University Archives, Duke University.
Fannie Yarbrough Mitchell papers, 1937-1977.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1961
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965
  - Annual reports, 1938-1943
  - Annual reports, 1943-1945
  - Annual reports, 1973
  - Placement by state, commercial, 1948-1955
  - Placement by state, commercial, 1955-1963
  - Placement of women graduates, 1961-1965
  - Placement in Europe (especially England), contacts, correspondence, referrals, ca. 1963-1968
  - Southern Education Foundation Internship negotiations, 1966-1967
  - Recruited opinions of Appointments Office interactions, 1961
  - Appointments Office history, ca. 1938-1943
  - Appointments Office, general notices to students, undated
  - Appointments Office, budgets, 1965-1968
  - Appointments Office, fliers, undated
  - Short writings, Fannie Y. Mitchell, ca. 1950-1970
  - Short writings, Manual for College Placement, regarding Chapter 5, "Staff", by Fannie Mitchell, undated
  - Speeches, general Appointments Office, undated
  - Speeches, to students, "If you think I am going to make…", undated
  - Speeches, to students, "Success in seeking a job…", undated
  - Speeches, to students, "I might as well tell you…", 1959
  - Speeches, to students interested in doing research, undated
  - Speeches, to students, salaries, undated.
  - Speeches, to students, general Appointments Office, undated.
  - Speeches, women in the workforce, "How could I be so presumptuous …," undated
  - Speeches, women in the workforce, "Present Status of Women in Business and Profession," undated
  - Speeches, women's achievement, "A club woman is a woman with a club…", undated
  - Speeches, women's achievement, "This is a pleasant occasion for me…", undated
  - Speeches, to engineering students, undated
  - Speeches, to wives of engineering students, undated
  - Speeches, men in the workplace, "What recruiters want in a man…", undated
  - undated
  - Speeches, "Ivy Walls to Ivory Towers," 1965.
  - Speeches, to Raleigh Wake Personnel Club, 1957
  - Speeches, "How the N.C. Employment Security Commission and College Placement…", undated
  - Speeches, to professional bankers, undated
  - Fannie Mitchell, speaking engagements at conferences, general, ca. 1950-1960
  - Fannie Mitchell, speaking engagements at conferences, Duke University, 1962-1963
  - Fannie Mitchell, speaking engagements at conferences, Woman's College Development Advisory Committee, 1965-1966
  - Southern College Placement Association correspondence, 1952, 1960-1962
  - Southern College Placement Association, correspondence, 1963
  - Southern College Placement Association, correspondence, 1964
  - Southern College Placement Association, correspondence, 1965-1968
  - 1958-1966
  - College Placement Services, correspondence, 1958-1966
  - College Placement Services, correspondence, 1967-1968
  - College Placement Services, publications board, 1951-1955
  - Clippings, 1940-1969
  - Clippings, 1970-1978, undated
  - Photographs, "To the Administration Belles, James T. Cleland, 1948"
  - Fannie Mitchell Day flier, 1968
  - Class Reports, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Annual Report, 1990-1991
  - Career Center, 2000-
  - Conference on Career Choices, 1993-
  - Career Guide, 1991-1992
  - Report on the Class of 1992 - Class Reports